בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is
ד dalet and we pick up after the very bottom of ג
עמוד ב. gimmel amud bet.
Let's pick it up two lines from the bottom of ג עמוד
ב. gimmel amud bet. We did this yesterday but we'll start again
from this today. Okay, so we had a discussion before that אביי
Abaye in the name of רב נחמן Rav Nachman said that there
are two types of אמות, amos, one that is חמישה טפחים chamishah
tfachim and one that is שישה טפחים shishah tfachim and that you
always use the one that's more מחמיר, machmir, the wonderful type of
a system of a measurement system where there's no standardization. רבא
Rava is not as extreme, but he still does have some type
of a variance. רבא משמיה דרב נחמן אמר כל אמות באמות בת
ששה. Rava mishmei d'Rav Nachman amar kol amos b'amos bat shishah. Every
time we say an אמה amah we mean a six טפח tefach
אמה, amah, so there's not this huge gap between five טפח tefach
and six טפח tefach
אמה. amah. אלא הללו שוחקות והללו עצבות. Ella hallalu sochakos v'hallalu atzevos.
One are laughing and the other are sort of sad, you know,
distressed. Meaning that when you laugh your hand sort of shakes a
little bit, so is your when you measure the טפח tefach is
the טפח tefach tightly compressed or is the טפח tefach with a
little loosely held? So that's a difference. So there is a little
bit of a difference between how big one אמה amah is and
the other like a little variance and there you're always מחמיר machmir
with whatever direction makes the most sense. I mean whatever direction turns
out to be a חומרא. chumra. Thank you so
much. So מיתיבי, Meisivei, let's ask you on this on well let's
see who we're asking on but now we have two positions אביי
Abaye and רבא. Rava. Here we have a ברייתא braisa that says
כל אמות שאמרו חכמים באמה בת ששה ובלבד שלא יהו מכוונות. kol
amos she'amru chachamim b'amah bat shishah u'bilvad she'lo ye'u mechuvannos. All the
אמות amos that the חכמים chachamim said whenever they speak about something
having to be x number of אמות, amos, they're talking about a
six טפח tefach אמה, amah, top of ד עמוד א, dalet amud
aleph, but provided that they're not precise. Meaning well for רבא Rava
it's clear what it means. It says בשלמא לרבא, bishlama l'Rava, for
רבא Rava this is perfect because it says every we always have
a six טפח tefach אמה amah and what does it mean that
they're not precise? היכי דלהויין הללו שוחקות והללו עצבות. Heichei d'lahavein hallalu
sochakos v'hallalu atzevos. But if depends whether you're being you know whether
the אמות amos is invalidating or validating. If the אמות amos is
invalidating so you're strict and you use the sad טפחים, tfachim, meaning
you use the more compressed measure. If the אמות amos is to
validate then you use the laughing ones, you use the slightly larger
measure. So there's it's not exactly standard but it always is six
טפח tefach with a little variance you know plus or minus half
an inch. Okay and you always go in whichever direction is the
more מחמיר machmir direction. That's what it means according to רבא. Rava.
אלא לאביי קשיא, Ella l'Abaye kashya, but for אביי Abaye it's a
big problem because אביי Abaye said the difference was five טפח tefach
versus six טפח tefach and this says it's always a six טפח
tefach אמה. amah. How do you deal with it? So אמר לך
אביי, amar lach Abaye, אביי Abaye will say to you, אימא אמת
כלאים באמה בת ששה. eima amas kilayim b'amah bat shishah. It shouldn't
read all אמות amos are six טפח tefach אמה. amah. It means
by כלאים, kilayim, all כלאים kilayim אמות amos are six טפח tefach
because by כלאים kilayim the need for x number of אמות amos
is to validate so we're always going to go by the larger
measure to be מחמיר. machmir.
So the גמרא Gemara says you can't say that. והא מדקתני סיפא,
V'ha midtani seifa, the end of that ברייתא braisa says רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר כל אמות שאמרו חכמים בכלאים באמה בת ששה ובלבד
שלא יהו מצומצמות. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer kol amos she'amru chachamim
b'kilayim b'amah bat shishah u'bilvad she'lo ye'u m'tzumtzamos. That רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says all the אמות amos
by כלאים kilayim are six טפחים tfachim and again they're not precise.
So מכלל michlal meaning it's either like you know like again here
in this case by כלאים kilayim since we're being מחמיר machmir by
doing more it would mean that they would be loose אמות. amos.
But anyway you see it's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel that says that כלאים kilayim is six טפחים. tfachim. מכלל דתנא
קמא Michlal d'tanna kamma from this you can infer that the תנא
קמא tanna kamma who did not say כלאים kilayim and said six
טפחים, tfachim, otherwise רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and
תנא קמא tanna kamma are saying the same thing. תנא קמא Tanna
kamma says six טפחים tfachim not precise, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says by כלאים kilayim six טפחים tfachim and not
precise. Clearly what they're debating is whether it's only by כלאים kilayim
or by everything. מכלל דתנא קמא כל אמות קאמר. Michlal d'tanna kamma
kol amos ka'amar. The תנא קמא tanna kamma is saying all אמות
amos are six טפח tefach אמה. amah. So it seems very clear
that according to the תנא קמא tanna kamma you always measure by
a six טפח tefach אמה amah like רבא Rava not like אביי.
Abaye. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר לך אביי, amar lach Abaye,
אביי Abaye will say to you, ולאו מי איכא רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל דקאי כוותי? v'lav mi'ika Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel d'kai k'vasi? Okay
so fine you proved the תנא קמא tanna kamma goes against me.
I still got רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that
backs me up. He says only by כלאים. kilayim. So אנא דאמרי
כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. ana de'amari k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. I'll say
like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So what do
we have right now? We have that אביי Abaye and רבא Rava
both agree that you don't have an exactly you know standardized measurement
system. According to אביי Abaye you have a huge variance, you have
an אמה amah that sometimes can be measured either by חמישה טפחים
chamishah tfachim or שישה טפחים shishah tfachim and according to רבא Rava
you have a variance of tightly compressed טפחים tfachim or loose טפחים,
tfachim, so you know let's say plus or minus half an inch.
Okay so it's a much less of a variance and everybody agrees
that you do the more strict measure based on the case whether
it's more strict to use the large measure or the small measure.
But here we have a debate of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel and the חכמים chachamim that seem to be debating
whether you use the six טפח tefach אמה amah in all cases
or just by כלאים. kilayim. So אביי Abaye says all right. So
I'll side with רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. He
says just by כלאים, Kilayim, but I have to admit that the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says you use a six טפח Tefach אמה
Ammah in all cases and that’s against me, cause I would say
you very often use the five טפח Tefach אמה. Ammah. So that's
what the גמרא Gemara now says. אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. So
according to אביי Abaye there's no way out of it. There clearly
is a debate of the תנאים Tannaim whether you use a five
טפח Tefach אמה Ammah or six טפח Tefach אמה Ammah in all
the times. According to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
you only use a six טפח Tefach אמה Ammah by כלאים, Kilayim,
other times five טפח, Tefach, you always do what’s more מחמיר. machmir.
But according to תנא קמא Tanna Kamma you always use a six
טפח Tefach אמה. Ammah. Okay, so that’s clearly אביי's Abaye position is
only backed up by רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
and the חכמים Chachamim go against it.
Where are we? תנאי. Tannai. לרבא מי לימא
תנאי? LeRava mi leima Tannai?
According to רבא Rava though, is it necessarily a debate of תנאים?
Tannaim? Because again, the ברייתא Braita said that all אמות ammot are
six טפח, Tefach, which is what רבא Rava said. But then רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said by כלאים Kilayim it’s
six טפח. Tefach. So that seems to be arguing on רבא Rava
because that seems to say only by כלאים Kilayim is it six
טפח, Tefach, by other things it’s something else. So אמר לך רבא,
Amar lach Rava, so רבא Rava will say to you, no, I
can even have רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel go
like me. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל הא אתא לאשמועינן. Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel ha ata l'ashmoeinan. When רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel says כלאים Kilayim is a six טפח Tefach אמה, Ammah, not
precise. What he's really telling you is אמת כלאים לא יצמצם. Ammat
Kilayim lo yetzamtzem. So what he's really telling you is it's not
six טפח. Tefach. Six טפח Tefach we take for granted, everything is
a six טפח Tefach אמה. Ammah. What he's telling me is when
I measure the כלאים Kilayim six טפח, Tefach, then I do it
not as the tight six טפח Tefach אמה Ammah but I do
it as the loose six טפח Tefach אמה. Ammah. Right, again, the
basic rule is,
excuse me,
sometimes a measurement qualifies something for to be acceptable, sometimes it
disqualifies. If it qualifies, then you're strict if you take the bigger
measurement, you mean you have to reach a higher threshold before it's
acceptable. If it disqualifies, then being strict is taking the shorter measuring
stick because then it becomes invalid at an earlier stage. So by
כלאים, Kilayim, we need a certain distance in order to allow you
to qualify, in order to allow you to plant in that field.
So you're going to take the larger measurement by כלאים. Kilayim. By
something like a סוכה Sukkah or a מבוי, Mavoy, if it's too
big or whatever, too wide, the opening, then it's invalid, we're going
to use the smaller measure. Okay? Is that clear? That's the basic
agreement here, the basic position of אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava. But
now
רבא Rava has to deal with the fact that רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel seems to say... so רבא Rava said
but you always use six טפחים. tefachim. So what do you do
with the fact that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
said only by כלאים? Kilayim? So רבא Rava is saying no, no,
no, what he's not saying is that only by כלאים Kilayim you
use six טפחים. tefachim. You always use six טפחים. tefachim. But by
כלאים Kilayim the six טפחים tefachim is the looser six טפחים tefachim
because again, that's the stricter one, it's the bigger measure. So the
emphasis on רבן שמעון בן גמליאל's Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel חידוש chiddush
is the מצומצמות, metzumtzamot, it's not יצמצם, yetzamtzem, it's not the tight,
but it's the looser one, it's the bigger six טפח. Tefach. So
the גמרא Gemara says if that's true, ולימא אמת כלאים לא יצמצם.
V'leima ammat Kilayim lo yetzamtzem. So then just say fine, why doesn't
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel just say when you
get to כלאים Kilayim don't use a tight measurement? באמה בת שיתא
למעוטי מאי? B'amma bat shita l'atuyei mai? Why does he have to
say you use a six טפח Tefach measurement that is not tight?
It seems to suggest that by other things, by all other things
you'd use a five טפח Tefach אמה, Ammah, which seems to be
אביי's Abaye position. So the גמרא Gemara says למעוטי מאי, L'atuyei mai,
what's that coming to exclude? לאו למעוטי אמת סוכה ואמת מבוי? Lav
l'atuyei ammat Sukkah v'ammat Mavoy? Isn't that suggesting that according to רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel only by כלאים Kilayim you
use a six טפח Tefach אמה, Ammah, but by things like a
סוכה Sukkah and a מבוי Mavoy you use a five טפח Tefach
אמה? Ammah? So again at least רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel seems to be going like אביי, Abaye, emphasize six טפחים
tefachim by the כלאים. Kilayim. So the גמרא Gemara says לא למעוטי
אמת יסוד ואמת סובב. Lo, l'atuyei ammat yesod v'ammat sovev. There's one
area that even רבא Rava will admit is a five טפח Tefach
אמה. Ammah. And that is not about סוכה Sukkah or מבוי Mavoy
or כלאים. Kilayim. According to nobody, everybody says you always do six
טפח Tefach אמה Ammah by all those real-world things that we actually
deal with in הלכה. halacha. And even רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel doesn't debate that. The reason רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel emphasizes כלאים Kilayim is that to say yes,
to imply there is one area that you use a five טפח
Tefach אמה Ammah but nothing that has to deal with us nowadays.
And what does that have to do with? The parameters, the dimensions
of the מזבח Mizbe'ach in the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. And there,
for some purposes, you use a five טפח Tefach אמה. Ammah. Let's
take a look. דכתיב, D'chtiv, so the אמה ammah of the יסוד,
yesod, יסוד yesod is the foundation of the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. The מזבח
Mizbe'ach basically was constructed... gotta get... not everybody can see that. Okay,
we'll use this.
Perfect.
There we go.
This is sort of... the מזבח Mizbe'ach was basically constructed like this.
Okay, and then maybe... like that. Okay, anyway, so you had the
foundation, right? Then you went up a bit. Then you had the
walk around, the סובב. sovev. This is the יסוד, yesod, this is
the סובב. sovev. Walk around, and then you went up higher. higher
and then you got to the very top. And at the top
you had corners, you know, four at the four corners and so
on. So the one of the measurements for this base here and
one of the measurements for the walk around, when it measures in
אמה ammah is a five טפח tefach אמה. ammah. Let's take a
look. And that's the one place that even אביי Abaye רבא Rava
would say, at least there I'll concede and that's what רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is alluding to.
Maybe it was hybrid?
I know so I know so we'll talk about it. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: דכתיב, dechesiv,
the פסוק pasuk says... דכתיב, dechesiv,
ואלה מדות המזבח באמות. ve'eileh midos hamizbeiach ba'amos. This
is a פסוק pasuk from יחזקאל. Yechezkel. It's actually quite interesting that
we're learning from יחזקאל. Yechezkel. I mean we just read actually the
you know פרשת החודש Parshas Hachodesh הפטרה haftorah from יחזקאל. Yechezkel. There's
so much in יחזקאל's Yechezkel description of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
how they would do the עבודה avodah that's not consistent with what
it says in the תורה. Torah. So you know it's one of
the גמרא Gemara says that they wanted לגנוז lignoze ספר sefer יחזקאל,
Yechezkel, there's all these contradictions. But anyway here we're learning from it.
These are the measurements of the altar, of the מזבח mizbeiach באמות,
ba'amos, in אמות. amos. Now אמה, ammah,
אמה וטפח. ammah vatefach. So an אמה ammah and an אמה ammah
and a טפח. tefach. Now what does that mean? So basically I'll
read the way there's like two versions of רש"י, Rashi, I'll read
it the second way. What it means is that preceding this there
was a lot of descriptions of measurements of you know of of
the altar and other parts about of the מקדש. Mikdash. And it
says all of those were in the big אמה. ammah. An אמה
ammah that is an אמה ammah plus a טפח tefach of the
small אמה, ammah, right? Because a six טפח tefach אמה, ammah, so
if you have a five טפח tefach אמה, ammah, it's one אמה
ammah plus a טפח tefach to get to the bigger אמה. ammah.
So that's where we're getting this idea that there's a six טפח
tefach אמה ammah and a five טפח tefach אמה. ammah. So everything
mentioned before was the measurement of the מזבח mizbeiach באמות ba'amos which
is an אמה ammah which is an אמה וטפח, ammah vatefach, which
is an אמה ammah and a טפח tefach of the smaller אמה.
ammah. And now as far as the smaller אמה ammah is concerned,
that's how this is being read, וחיק האמה ואמה רוחב וגבולה אל
שפתה סביב זרת האחד וזה גב המזבח. vecheik ha'ammah ve'ammah rochav ugvulah
el sefasah saviv zeires ha'echad vezeh gav hamizbeiach. So now this however
the everything else in this פסוק pasuk is the smaller אמה. ammah.
So now what's everything else in this פסוק? pasuk? We're going to
say: חיק האמה, cheik ha'ammah, so the חיק cheik the belt like
of the אמה, ammah, זה יסוד, zeh yesod, that's the base. Okay
so there one of the ways it's measured is by אמה ammah
is by
that אמה ammah is a five טפח tefach אמה. ammah.
ואמה רוחב ve'ammah rochav זה סובב, zeh sovev, and and אמה ammah
width is the walk-around. וגבולה אל שפתה סביב, ugvulah el sefasah saviv,
the border by its edge all around, אלו הקרנות, elu hakranos, those
are the horns at the top. So all of those were an
אמה ammah by an אמה ammah and those were all וזה גב
המזבח vezeh gav hamizbeiach and this is the top of the altar,
זה מזבח הזהב zeh mizbeiach hazahav which was also an אמה ammah
by an אמה. ammah. So all of those things which were an
אמה ammah high or an אמה ammah in or an אמה ammah
by an אמה, ammah, all of those were measured with the five
טפח tefach אמה ammah and that's at least a case that I'll
agree says רבא Rava that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel is saying is a five טפח tefach אמה. ammah. Now Michael
correctly says that they're not all the same direction that you're measuring
the אמה ammah with. It gets a little complicated.
If you look רש"י Rashi says the last the first wide line
of רש"י Rashi says or the last narrow line he says: בפרק
שתי הלחם מפרש ליה להאי קרא דאמה יסוד דקאמי דקתני, beperek shtei
halechem mefareish lei lehai kra de'ammah yesod dekami d'katani, that when we
say the אמה ammah of the base is the small one, לא
ברוחב כניסת היסוד אלא בגובה עלייתו. lav berochav knisas hayesod ella begovah
aliyaso. So when we say it's an אמה ammah the יסוד yesod
goes up an אמה ammah and in an אמה. ammah. So the
up an אמה ammah is the five טפח. tefach. The in is
six טפח. tefach. Okay and it's the opposite... what?
Are you all confused? And it's the opposite by the סובב. sovev.
It goes up when it goes up, it goes up five normal
אמות, amos, but when it goes in, it goes in a five
טפח tefach אמה. ammah. And when it gets to the horns they're
one אמה ammah by one אמה ammah in both directions five טפחים.
tefachim. What can I tell you? Very strange. All right anyway that's
where you are and and now we get to move on. Okay?
So there's a debate of is there there are two types of
אמות amos a five טפח tefach six טפח, tefach, according to רבא
Rava the five טפח tefach one is safely ensconced in the area
in discussions about the מזבח mizbeiach and about the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and we don't have to worry about it and we can
just focus on the six טפח tefach אמה. ammah. According to אביי
Abaye they both play a role. But even according to רבא Rava
there is some variance of how tightly you measure the אמה. ammah.
They didn't have a National Bureau Standards at those days and therefore
you are you have to be מחמיר machmir in both directions. Now
we get onto another related discussion but a quite fascinating one, one
that's quoted in many different גמרות. Gemaras.
אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi
amar Rav, said רבי חייא בר אשי Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi in
the name of רב: Rav: שיעורין חציצין ומחיצין הלכה למשה מסיני. shiurin
chatzitzin umechitzin halacha leMoshe miSinai. It's a nice little sort of ring
to it, sometimes you get this also because of an oral tradition
so like שיעורין חציצין ומחיצין shiurin chatzitzin umechitzin it almost rhymes. Measurements,
חציצות chatzitzas which are blockages, you know things that that interfere with
the water touching the body, it's a חציצה chatzitza or you know
an object when you put it in a מקוה mikvah and a
מחיצה mechitza the laws about מחיצה mechitza are all הלכה למשה מסיני
halacha leMoshe miSinai are traditions
from
משה. Moshe. Well we're going to talk about all of this. No,
no, no, not the מחיצות mechitzos surely. Okay, we're going to talk
about
this. Okay, let's take a look. Now we unpack this. שיעורין, Shiurin,
so the שיעורין, shiurin, like now we're always dealing with a שיעור,
shiur, right? How סוכות Sukkot 20 אמות amos high, 4 by 4
אמות amos wide, or 7 and a משהו mashu by 7 and
a משהו mashu is a מבוי mavoi 20 by 10. Now of
course the מבוי mavoi is rabbinic, but you know everything has minimum
and maximum sizes. How much מצה matzah do you have to eat
on פסח, Pesach, how much wine do you have to drink, right?
So שיעורין, shiurin, so the גמרא Gemara says דאורייתא הוא. d'Oraisa hu.
It's from the פסוק, pasuk, it's not only הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha
l'Moshe m'Sinai. דכתיב, Dechsiv, the פסוק pasuk says ארץ חטה
ושערה וגفن ותאנה ורמון ארץ זית שמן ודבש. Eretz chitah u'se'orah v'gefen
u'se'enah v'rimon eretz zeis shemen u'devash. אמר רב חנן, Amar Rav Chanan,
כל הפסוק הזה לשיעורין נאמר. kol hapasuk hazeh l'shiurin ne'emar. This entire
פסוק pasuk is said regarding regarding using these different the seven species
of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for measuring sizes. חטה, Chitah, wheat, דתנן,
de'tnan, we taught in a משנה. Mishnah. הנכנס לבית המנוגע וכליו על
כתפיו וסנדליו וטבעותיו בידיו. Hanechnas l'veis hamenuga u'cheilav al kesafav v'sandalav v'tab'osov
b'yadav. Somebody goes into a house that has leprosy, meaning the house
itself has spots on it, right, like the תורה Torah describes. Now
the הלכה halacha is, is that it says כל הבא אל הבית,
kol habah el habayis, anybody that comes into the house will be
יטמא. yitamei. And then it says והאוכל בבית, v'ha'ochel babayis, and if
somebody eats in the house, then רחץ את בגדיו במים, rachatz es
begadav bamayim, then his garments become טמא tamei and he have to
cleanse his garments. So what the rabbis say is the following is:
A, it only applies to garments that you're wearing, בגדיו. begadav. If
you actually come in with a suitcase and you have clothes in
your suitcase, then it has nothing to do with eating in the
house. It's just the clothes came into the house like anything else
comes into a house and they become טמא tamei automatically. The פסוק
pasuk is talking about the clothes you're wearing. And then the rabbis
say, it's not only, it doesn't mean or not limited to eating
in the house. It means if you stay in the house long
enough to eat a meal. So the הלכה halacha is, if you
go, anything that comes into a house that has צרעת tzaraas automatically
becomes טמא tamei with the one exception of the clothes on your
body. And they only become טמא tamei if you stay in the
house long enough to eat a meal. So that's what this משנה
Mishnah says. הנכנס לבית המנוגע, Hanechnas l'veis hamenuga, somebody goes into a
house with צרעת, tzaraas, וכליו על כתפיו u'cheilav al kesafav and you
have your garments on your shoulder, you're not wearing them, וסנדליו וטבעותיו
בידיו v'sandalav v'tab'osov b'yadav and you're holding on to your, you know,
your rings and your sandals, הוא והם טמאים מיד, hu v'heim t'mei'im
miyad, then everything is טמא tamei automatically. They're not the clothes on
your back. היה לבוש בכליו, Hayah lavush b'cheilav, if you're wearing your
garments, וסנדליו ברגליו v'sandalav b'raglav and your shoes are on your feet,
וטבעותיו באצבעותיו v'tab'osov b'etzbe'osov and your rings are on your fingers, not
as opposed before it said in your hands, here it's on your
fingers, הוא טמא מיד, hu tamei miyad, you're טמא tamei automatically,
or immediately I should say, והם טהורים עד שישהא, v'heim t'horim ad
sheyis'ha'eh, and they become טהורים t'horim only after you wait as long
as it takes to eat a meal, כדי אכילת פרס, kdei achilas
pras, the time it takes to eat a פרס, pras, a half
a loaf of bread, because a standard loaf of bread was considered
to be two meals worth. We will see about making an עירוב
eiruv with a loaf of bread and you have to make an
עירוב eiruv with food for two meals. So a standard loaf of
bread was eating two meals. How much of a half of a
loaf of a standard loaf? So רש"י Rashi says it's four ביצים.
beitzim. It actually boils down to a debate between whether it's eight
or nine כזיתים. kezaysim. Okay, is this a standard half a loaf
of bread, כדי אכילת פרס. kdei achilas pras. Now what type? Small.
Now what type of bread is it? פת חטין ולא פת שעורין,
Pas chittin v'lo pas se'orin, wheat bread and not barley bread. That's
why the, that's what we learn out from the word wheat, that
when we measure the time it takes to eat bread, we measure
by wheat bread. Okay, מיסב ואוכל, Meisav v'ochel, and when you're reclining
and eating, not standing and eating, בליפתן, b'lifan, when you're dipping it
into some type of a sauce. Now
רש"י Rashi says, first of all,
with all these criteria, only when you're reclining, when you're dipping it
into a sauce, right, if you ask me, I get that image
in my head, somebody's reclining, eating, first of all, פסח Pesach right,
but it's also because, you know, that's how they ate in certainly,
you know, in the Roman times, but I also get the sense
that that makes it go faster, slower, right, you're, you know, you're
being very relaxed as you eat. רש"י Rashi interprets it all, all
these things make it go faster, make it a shorter time, that
he's, because he assumes that first of all wheat bread you eat
quicker than barley bread, which is I assume true, I assume it's
easier to digest wheat bread. Is that right? No?
It's heavier, it's denser, it doesn't grind down.
Yeah, that's what I would imagine. So once he assumes that wheat,
he says so wheat bread goes faster. He says so if you're
eating standing, somehow that means you're not focused on your eating, you're
moving around and therefore when you're reclining you're focused on your eating
and when you're putting it in a, in a sauce, that helps
you like eat it quicker because it makes it tastier or something.
So רש"י Rashi reads that all of these make that time go
faster. I will say that כדי אכילת פרס kdei achilas pras by
the way is a very important measurement not just for this principle
of צרעת, tzaraas, but since it's the definition of like the normal
time it takes to eat a meal, it's also the time to
which, you know, you can stretch out an eating process and it's
still considered one act of eating. So that goes
for like transgression. And eventually it collected it wouldn't be enough. You
have to eat a כזית kezayis in the time it takes to
eat a פרס. pras. And similarly for מצוות mitzvos like when you
come to eat מצה, matzah, you know you have to eat a
כזית kezayis in the time it takes to eat a פרס, pras,
which is why some people of course you know you'll see them
doing that because they measure everything לחומרא. l'chumra. They figure okay first
to measure the כזית kezayis of the מצה matzah we're going to
figure out how much we can pack in by getting rid of
all the air you know content of the מצה. matzah. And then
when we figure out how long it takes to eat a פרס,
pras, we're not going to figure out how long it takes to
eat a פרס pras of מצה. matzah. We're going to talk how
long would it take to eat a פרס pras of bread. So
now you have this much מצה matzah in two minutes. Okay but
anyway that is by the way an interesting debate whether you measure
כדי אכילת פרס kdei achilas pras as a function of the particular
thing that you're eating, you know how long would it take to
eat that amount of this thing or some type of abstractly anyway
but that becomes a very important שיעור. shiur. So that's what we
learn out from one of the things we learn out from the
fact that it says חטה chittah is that you measure it by
wheat bread. Now of course what the גמרא Gemara is going to
ask is there's so many other assumptions here that are not in
the פסוק pasuk right? Half a loaf and reclining and all these
types of things. You can't say that this is all from the
פסוק. pasuk. There's a lot of things that are being assumed here
that are not in the פסוק. pasuk.
So האוכל בבית ha'ochel babayis you said is not actually eating it's
the שיעור shiur to eat? Yes. What what do you do with
השוכב בבית? hashochev babayis? That's in the same פסוק. pasuk.
I'm trying to remember I think רש"י Rashi gets this down? No
check the רש"י. Rashi.
I don't know.
I'll get back to you.
I'm trying to remember if there's a separate שיעור shiur
for yeah I'll get back to you on that. Okay alright so
now okay so now the גמרא Gemara says where are we?
Okay. שעורה se'orah barley. דתנן detnan עצם כשעורה מטמא במגע ובמשא. etzem
k'se'orah metamei b'maga u'v'massa. That if you have a piece of bone
okay in order for something a dead body a corpse to cause
טומאה באהל tumah b'ohel under a roof it has to be you
know it has to be either a bone with flesh on it
it has to be a whole limb or you know or has
to be a כזית kezayis worth of flesh but if all you
have is bone and no flesh then if it's the size of
a barley bean which is quite small then it causes טומאה tumah
by touch and by carrying
but it will not cause טומאה tumah under a roof the amount
of if you have no flesh then you need a lot of
bones you need the most of the skeleton or the skull or
a different part you know significant amount of the bones in order
to cause טומאה tumah under a roof but even a tiny amount
causes טומאה tumah by touching or by carrying so that's what you
learn from שעורה se'orah a barley bean.
גפן gefen wine. כדי רביעית יין לנזיר. kdei revios yayin l'nazir. That
for a נזיר nazir only when he drinks a רביעית revios of
wine. Now you will notice that there is a problem with that
with the logic there meaning it's not normal until now we've been
saying use the thing to measure something else. How long does it
take you to eat a meal we mean a meal of wheat
bread that's what we learn from wheat. How much bone causes טומאה
tumah the size of a barley bean. Here what are we learning
from wine? A רביעית revios of wine for a נזיר. nazir. First
of all we already know that a נזיר nazir can't drink wine
so you don't learn that from the word wine. Second of all
you know
it's not telling us the size so what does it really tell
us? So that's what this big תוספות Tosafos is about.
So the רביעית revios
is not telling us the size? It doesn't tell us רביעית. revios.
חטה chittah told us a certain way of measuring wheat bread. שעורה
se'orah told us a way of measuring with the size of a
barley. Wine doesn't tell us a way of measuring the amount of
wine that a נזיר nazir has to drink. So רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafos discuss this and the basic answer is
that the way you measure is by water displacement. And the question
and the thing is what do you use? Use water displacement or
wine displacement? You know if you have an exact cup that's the
size of a רביעית revios and you want to put stuff in
of course if you know the point is why would you have
to displace if you're putting in a liquid? So some say that
the נזיר nazir drank wine which is what it does say but
we're talking here let's say ate grapes and you need to measure
it by water displacement. So do you put them in to see
if it displaces a רביעית revios do you put them in a
measuring cup that has in it water or has in it wine?
What difference does it make? Well wine has a greater surface tension.
So if you try to do the water displacement trick with wine
then it will take more to displace a רביעית revios worth of
wine.
No I still don't know that wine has greater surface tension.
No that's what תוספות Tosafos claims. It's got to be true תוספות
Tosafos says it.
Hydrogen bonding and if you have wine then you've got different sediments
in there and you're going to affect the hydrogen bonding so you're
not going to have surface tension.
Assuming sediment-free
wine then if you have filtered wine would you
have...
Wine back then had far more alcohol than today's wine, but it
had to be diluted before they could drink it, so that by
stop my thought.
Well, I don't know, but then the question is maybe we are
talking about undiluted. Anyway, that's the way they try to explain it,
that we're using the wine as a system of measuring the displacement,
and therefore somehow we use wine to measure rather than water to
measure, but it's a hard— it's a hard like you know— it's
a hard piece to unpack. תאנה, Te'enah, now, a fig, כגרוגרת kegogeres
להוצאת שבת, lehotzas Shabbos, we remembered the you know two פרקים prakim
of שבת Shabbos about this, that when you carry out you know
something the size of a pressed fig, then you're חייב chayav for
carrying on שבת. Shabbos. רמון, Rimon, a pomegranate, דתנן, ketnan, כל כלי
בעלי בתים, kol kli ba'alei batim, שיעורן כרמונים, shiuran kerimonim, all vessels
of homeowners, if it has a hole the size of a pomegranate,
which is a pretty big hole, then it stops being considered a
vessel. Meaning, if you're— if you're doing it for sale, even a
tiny little hole you won't sell it, and then it stops being
a vessel. If you're a storekeeper, but if you're a homeowner, so
if something has a little hole in it, you stop using it
for keeping your flour and you start using it for keeping your
olives, it gets a bigger hole, you start using it for keeping
your apples, it gets a bigger hole, you start using it for
keeping your pomegranates. Once it's got the— a hole the size of
a pomegranate, then already you throw it out. So only when it
has the hole the size of a pomegranate does it stop being
considered a vessel. ארץ זית שמן, Eretz zeis shemen, olive oil, so
now we're back to olives, ארץ שכל שיעוריה כזיתים, eretz shekol shiureha
kezaysim, a land that all of the שיעורים shiurim are כזית, kezayis,
כזית kezayis is like the universal שיעור. shiur. So the גמרא Gemara
says כל שיעוריה כזיתים, kol shiureha kezaysis, literally all of the שיעורים?
shiurim? האיכא הני דאמרי, haika hani de'amrin, what about everything you just
said? כגרוגרת, kegogeres,
שעורה, se'orah, so it says אלא, ella, okay, אימא ארץ שרוב שיעוריה
כזיתים, eima eretz sherov shiureha kezaysim, fine it was exaggerating, but many
many things, most things we measure by a כזית. kezayis. If you
want just an example, רש"י Rashi gives you, I think the third
wide-line רש"י, Rashi, אכילת חלב, achilas cheilev, ודם, vedam, ונותר, venosar, ופגול,
upiggul, וטמא, vetamei, ונבילה, veniveilah, ובהמה טמאה. uveheimah temeiah. There are a
lot of אסור assur things that to eat, so everything that is
אסור assur to eat pretty much is a כזית kezayis and everything
that is a מצוה mitzvah to eat is a כזית. kezayis. So
many— most things are measured by a כזית. kezayis. Okay, דבש, dvash,
honey, which is— which is date honey, ככותבת הגסה ליום הכפורים, kokesevet
hagassah leyom hakippurim, a fat date for יום הכפורים, Yom Kippur, that's
the amount of food you have to eat to transgress, that's the
one thing that doesn't go by a כזית kezayis because that's not
about the act of eating, that's about
not sort of you know afflicting yourself, giving— and therefore it goes
by a day— you know, it goes by a different measure.
So the גמרא Gemara says ותסברה, utisbra, okay, so there you see,
what do you mean it's הלכה למשה מסיני? halacha lemoshe misinai? They're
all based on the פסוק. pasuk. So the גמרא Gemara says ותסברה,
utisbra, does that really make sense what you're trying to argue, that
it's all based on the פסוק? pasuk? שיעורין מכתב כתיבי, shiurin michtav
ketivi, what I don't get it, are they written? You know the
פסוק pasuk just says חטה שעורה גפן תאנה, chitta, se'ora, gefen, te'enah,
you're the one that came along and decided that what you know,
to interpret it to mean a שיעור, shiur, it could also ask
it's not just that it's not clear that it's talking about שיעורין,
shiurin, but then what to apply the שיעורין shiurin to, how do
you know that the barley goes to the bone, how do you
know wheat is supposed to be about the time it takes to
eat wheat bread and all those other assumptions. So there's plenty of
stuff we're reading into the פסוק pasuk that isn't there. אלא
הלכתא נינהו, Ella hilchesa ninhu, it's all הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha lemoshe
misinai, ואסמכינהו רבנן אקראי, veasmihinu rabanan akrai, the rabbis just connected it
to the פסוק. pasuk. It's interesting because you could have said you
know something a little bit more of a middle ground, that there
was הלכה למשה מסיני halacha lemoshe misinai how to read the פסוק,
pasuk, but anyway, but it sort of says no no no, all
of these issues about the שיעורים shiurim is all הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha lemoshe misinai. So all the minimums and the maximums and a
lot of עירובין eiruvin makes sense that this is being introduced right
here in the beginning, because I mean to one hand it's being
introduced because of you know because it tie— because we are discussing
the שיעורים shiurim which measuring 20 and then it was חמש טפחים,
chamesh tefachim, ששה טפחים, shesha tefachim, and now we're discussing in general,
by the way that's what this is doing here, the whole idea
of measurements and measurements is הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha lemoshe misinai. But
a lot of עירובין eiruvin is about measurements and a lot of
it is rabbinic, so clearly that would be rabbinic, but here it's
saying that everything that is a biblical measurement is all הלכה למשה
מסיני. halacha lemoshe misinai. Now,
חציצין, chatzitzin, how about the idea of a חציצה, chatzitza, an obstruction
between the body and water that that is now seen— that that
is a הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai, it doesn't say in
the פסוק pasuk anywhere that that's a problem. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute,
חציצין דאורייתא נינהו, chatzitzin de'oraisa ninhu,
that's biblical, דכתיב, dechisiv, ורחץ את כל בשרו, verachatz es kol besaro,
he should— you should
wash your entire body,
so שלא יהא דבר חוצץ בין בשרו למים, shelo yehei davar chotzetz
bein besaro lemayim, that there should not be something interrupting your— now
of course it would be better if the פסוק pasuk said כל
בשרו במים kol besaro bamayim because then it's saying that it has
to be your flesh with the water, nothing can interrupt, but anyway,
but that's not actually in the פסוק. pasuk.
ורחץ בשרו במים ולא במי השם? Barachatz besaro bamayim u'lav hasham?
Right,
so maybe that would be— it would have been better to take
out the כל kol rather than— but anyway, but here it says—
but it's going to דרשן darshen כל kol in a minute. Anyway,
there are פסוקים pesukim that say בשרו במים, besaro bamayim, so we
say that that means your entire— that there cannot be anything obstructing
between your flesh and the water. במים, Bamayim, what does it mean
in water? במי מקוה. Bemei mikvah. It doesn't mean any water, it
means water of a מקוה mikva because it's true, most of the
time the תורה Torah just says wash your clothes, wash your body,
it doesn't say מקוה. mikva.
וכל בשרו במים, Vechol besaro bamayim, כל בשרו, kol besaro, all your
body, מים שכל גופו עולה בהן. mayim shekol gufo oleh bahen. So
your entire body has to go into them, meaning you can't do
part of your body, one limb at a time. You have to
do your whole body at once, and it has to be—the מקוה
mikva has to hold the amount of water that a whole body
can submerge. וכמה הן? Vechamah hen? And what is that size? אמה
על אמה ברום ג' אמות. amah al amah berum gimmel amot. An
אמה amah by an אמה, amah, and an אמה amah is about
a foot and a half, by a foot and a half, by
an אמה amah by three אמות, amot, by four and a half
feet. So that maybe is the size of a short person, maybe
if you're like, I don't know, crunch a little bit. People were
shorter then. And anyway, ושיערו חכמים, veshiaru chachamim, actually, from the גמרא,
Gemara, from other things it seems clear that that three אמות amot
was till shoulder height. So it's interesting though that they only had
to go three אמות. amot. Maybe they did assume you weren't standing
totally straight. Anyway, how much is this a three cubic אמות, amot,
אמה על אמה ברום ג' אמות? amah al amah berum gimmel amot?
ושיערו חכמים מקוה מ' סאה. Veshiaru chachamim mikva mem seah. That's equal
to 40 סאה. seah. That's our measurement of the minimum size of
a מקוה. mikva. By the way, it's very important because although obviously
it's you know, who's ever gonna have a מקוה mikva that tiny?
You know, I mean just think about it, like basically the amount
of water that would be exactly your own body displacement, or you
know, water displacement of your own body or less. But it's important
because even though we have much larger מקואות, mikvaot, the way our
מקוה mikva works is that you have a lot of piped in
water, you know, and it's connected to a smaller hidden like you
know area of collected rainwater. And that collected rainwater is the real
מקוה. mikva. And it makes the מקוה mikva that has that nice
clean piped in water כשר kosher because they're connected through a hole.
So the question is, how big does that מקוה mikva have to
be, the one that has the collected rainwater? And that is this
40 סאה, seah, which is learned from this idea of the water
that your whole body could fit
into. Okay, so anyway, so that's we learn a lot of important
things from that פסוק. pasuk. So you see we learn רחיצה. rechitza.
So what do you mean that חציצה chatzitza is הלכה למשה מסיני?
Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai? It's based on the פסוק. pasuk. So the גמרא
Gemara says, כי איצטריך הילכתא, ki itztarich hilchata, okay, here's what we
need the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai for: לשערו, lesaaro,
for the issue of your hair. Because that mentioned בשרו, besaro, your
flesh. How do we know your hair has to go into the
מקוה? mikva? Or how do we know a חציצה chatzitza is a
problem with your hair? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבה בר
רב הונא, amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna, like Rabbah bar Rav Huna
says, דאמר רבה בר רב הונא, damar Rabbah bar Rav Huna, נימא
אחת קשורה חוצצת. nima achat keshura chotzetet. That's and here I'll show
you the חציצה's chatzitza's a problem by hair. Because he says if
you have one hair tied upon itself, like a knot in one
strand of hair, that's a חציצה, chatzitza, because that makes a very
tight knot, and the water can't get in between into the you
know into the place that's being covered, that the hair is covering
itself. שלוש אינן חוצצות. Shalosh einan chotzetzot. If there's three hairs tied
on themselves, not three individually, but three together tied in a knot,
so then it's actually not a חציצה, chatzitza, because the knot can't
be as tight, and we assume water can get in. שתים איני
יודע.
Shtayim
eini yodea.
If it's two hairs, I don't know whether it's a חציצה chatzitza
or not. So I know one is not good, three is good,
I'm not sure about two. But what's relevant for us is that
the idea of חציצה chatzitza applies to hair. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ah, when we say חציצה's chatzitza's דאורייתא, Deoraita, the פסוק pasuk
says בשרו, besaro, flesh. Well, I'm telling you that with the הלכה
למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai it shows חציצה's chatzitza's a problem by
hair. So the גמרא Gemara says, שערו נמי דאורייתא הוא. saaro nami
Deoraita hu. That's also biblical. דתניא, Detanya, it's taught in a ברייתא,
braita, ורחץ את כל בשרו, verachatz et kol besaro, the את, et,
right, is a you know identifies the object of the verb, but
here it's seen as an extra word. את Et means את הטפל
לבשרו, et hatafel lebesaro, the thing that is an adjunct to the
flesh. וזהו שער. Vezehu sear. And that is a hair. So from
the word את et we learn the שער, sear, and you have
the same דרשה drasha of במים, bamayim, the hair has to touch
directly the water and there can't be a חציצה. chatzitza. So the
גמרא Gemara says, no. כי אתא הילכתא לרובו ולמיעוטו ולמקפיד ולשאינו מקפיד.
Ki ata hilchata lerubo ulemieuto ulemakpid ulesheaino makpid. Okay, here's what you
need הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai for. Forget the hair. It's
about the parameters of what constitutes a חציצה, chatzitza, whether it's the
majority of the body or the minority, whether you're מקפיד, makpid, you
want it off your body, or you don't care that it's on
your body. And what does that mean? וכדרבי יצחק, Uchedirabi Yitzchak, like
Rabbi Yitzchak. דאמר רבי יצחק, Damar Rabi Yitzchak, Rabbi Yitzchak says a
very, very important principle here for הלכות halachot of חציצה. chatzitza. דאמר
רבי יצחק, Damar Rabi Yitzchak, דבר תורה רובו ומקפיד עליו חוצץ, devar
Torah rubo umakpid alav chotzetz, ושאינו מקפיד עליו אינו חוצץ. usheaino makpid
alav eino chotzetz. The only real חציצה chatzitza in the תורה Torah
would be something that covers the majority of your body and you
don't want it on. Hard to imagine what that would be. What
type of thing would cover—I mean, I guess if you fell in
like a mud pile or something, like a like a pot of
paint and it fell on your head and then you went straight
into the מקוה. mikva. But what type of a חציצה chatzitza is
going to be on the majority of your body? Now רש"י Rashi
says—now רש"י Rashi says majority of your hair. Now, sorry, חציצה chatzitza
is on majority of your hair. Now תוספות Tosafot interprets רש"י Rashi
to mean that on your body even a tiny thing would be
a חציצה. chatzitza. רש"י Rashi never said that and probably not what
רש"י Rashi meant at all. And then תוספות Tosafot disproves it anyway,
and the same is true about your body. But what—but the other
way of reading רש"י, Rashi, and this actually is a position that
other ראשונים rishonim say and it's a position of some of the
גאונים. Geonim. is that hair is considered separate from the rest of
your body. So when you say רוב rov the majority is a
biblical חציצה chatzitzah it says it's either the majority of your body
or the majority of your hair. Not the hair to exclude the
body, but if it's on the majority of your hair, that's also
a biblical problem even not the majority of your body which actually
is an issue because because you know, let's because if you have
something it is possible to have something on the majority of your
hair. I don't know let's say you have hair dye for example,
right? So now you can say that's אינו מקפיד, eino makpid, you
definitely want it on and so on there could be other things
that could be in your hair, but anyway, but then you could
be talking about a question about it's not enough to say that
it's אינו מקפיד, eino makpid, you know because there because once it's
the majority it really is a problem. Is hair dye considered חציצה?
chatzitzah? No, it's not because whatever I don't want to get in
I shouldn't have mentioned that. But anyway, let's read a little bit
more. But the first thing I want to say is so let's
read I should go back I jumped ahead. Okay, so דבר תורה
רובו ומקפיד עליו חוצץ devar Torah rubo u'makpid alav chotzeitz the majority
and you're מקפיד makpid is חוצץ. chotzeitz. That's biblical. Meaning you don't
want it on. ושאינו מקפיד v'she'eino makpid if you don't care whether
it's on or not, אינו חוצץ eino chotzeitz it's not a חציצה.
chatzitzah. וגזרו על רובו שאינו מקפיד v'gazru al rubo she'eino makpid now
rabbinically we said if it's on the majority of your body even
though you're אינו מקפיד eino makpid it's not a problem משום רובו
המקפיד mishum rubo hamakpid because it'll lead to a case of majority
and you are מקפיד. makpid. So we have to be גוזר gozeir
even one, biblically you need both of those criteria to be a
חציצה, chatzitzah, rabbinically even one is enough to be a חציצה. chatzitzah.
Now גזירה לגזירה. gezeirah l'gezeirah. Well, no, no, they're just one degree
removed. Only you still need one of them. וגם מיעוט המקפיד v'gam
mi'ut hamakpid or if it's a minority and you're מקפיד, makpid, which
is what most חציצות chatzitzos are about, מיעוט המקפיד mi'ut hamakpid משום
רובו המקפיד mishum rubo hamakpid that's not good because it'll lead to
a case of the majority and being מקפיד. makpid. So now the
גמרא Gemara says וליגזר נמי על מיעוטו שאינו מקפיד v'ligzar nami al
mi'uto she'eino makpid
why don't we גוזר gozeir on all חציצות chatzitzos even a minority
that you're אינו מקפיד eino makpid on משום מיעוט המקפיד mishum mi'ut
hamakpid because it'll lead to a case of a minority you are
מקפיד makpid on אי נמי משום רובו שאינו מקפיד i nami mishum
rubo she'eino makpid it'll lead to a majority that you're אינו מקפיד
eino makpid on. Meaning is that clear?
Right? It's like how to do this. Yeah, רוב, rov,
מיעוט, mi'ut, מקפיד, makpid, אינו מקפיד. eino makpid. Right? So biblically it's
only רוב rov that's מקפיד, makpid, the majority of your body that
you don't want on. Rabbinically it's something that's similar to it in
one way, either row or column. Either it has the רוב rov
quality or it has the מקפיד makpid quality. This is dissimilar in
two ways, right? It's neither the majority of the body nor is
it מקפיד. makpid. So the גמרא Gemara says okay but let's make
a גזירה gezeirah on this and it'll lead to one of these
boxes. Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara question and that's a גזירה
לגזירה. gezeirah l'gezeirah. So the גמרא Gemara says וליגזר נמי על מיעוט
שאינו מקפיד v'ligzar nami al mi'ut she'eino makpid why don't we say
that a minority that you're אינו מקפיד eino makpid is not good
משום מיעוט המקפיד mishum mi'ut hamakpid to lead to a minority you
are מקפיד makpid on
אי נמי משום רובו שאינו מקפיד i nami mishum rubo she'eino makpid
or lead to a majority that you're אינו מקפיד eino makpid on.
So היא גופא גזירה hi gufa gezeirah one minute, those things those
other boxes are themselves גזירה gezeirah ואנן ניקו וניגזר גזירה לגזירה v'anan
neiku v'nigzar gezeirah l'gezeirah you want us to make a גזירה gezeirah
to a גזירה? gezeirah? So therefore we're not going to do it.
And that is what the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai is
telling us. What is the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai telling
us? Presumably that even though biblically we learn that there's an idea
of חציצה, chatzitzah, comes along the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai
and actually teaches us a leniency and teaches us that only this
box is a חציצה chatzitzah biblically. The תורה Torah if you just
had the תורה Torah you would have thought that even any tiny
little obstruction would be a problem. It says there can't be anything
between my flesh and the water, who cares about רוב, rov, מיעוט,
mi'ut, מקפיד, makpid, אינו מקפיד? eino makpid? Everything would have been a
problem. Comes along the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai and says
only when it's the majority and you are מקפיד. makpid. So let
me now step back a little bit and say something about this
הלכה halacha and about the thing I was talking about before with
רש"י, Rashi, which is so first of all our מנהג minhag is
to take off, you know primarily it applies to women when they
go to the מקוה, mikvah,
to take off everything even a מיעוט שאינו מקפיד. mi'ut she'eino makpid.
But that's just a מנהג minhag and if there's a real reason
not to take it off then then that would be okay. Of
course once there's a reason not to take it off it often
becomes an אינו מקפיד. eino makpid. But anyway,
but that's the point. The point is that our מנהג minhag is
that even with the מיעוט mi'ut that's not מקפיד, makpid, right, to
take off everything, but again if there's like you know there's I've
heard a case like a woman came in with like this red
בענדל bendel around, you know you know they do this thing for
עין הרע, ayin hara, absolutely refused to take it off. So fine,
it's a מיעוט mi'ut she's not מקפיד makpid she wants it on,
so even though the מנהג minhag is to take it off but
if she really can't you don't. Then but everything else the biggest
issues come up with the מיעוט המקפיד mi'ut hamakpid because how many
things are on the majority of your body, right? And but there's
a lot of things that are on the minority of your body
like if you left a little nail polish or you know very
often there's like there's like medical things or stitches or other types
of
issues. Now stitches and bandages, right, and so on. A cast, all
those issues.
A lot of those things logically would fall in the category of
אינו מקפיד, Eino Makpid, you know, but there are some very strict
opinions of what you need to define something as אינו מקפיד. Eino
Makpid. Part of the question around that has to do with what's
the logic behind by אינו מקפיד. Eino Makpid. Rashi by אינו מקפיד
עליו Eino Makpid Alav says הוי כגופו. Havi Kegufo. ואף על גב
דעביד לרווחא ולא לחיותא. Veaf Al Gav Deavid Lerevacha Velo Lechiyuta. אינו
מקפיד Eino Makpid makes it like part of your body. So if
you have to say you have to positively make this as part
of your body, that's a pretty high threshold to reach, although even
with that you would say certain types of things like stitches, you
know, you would argue but still maybe casts or braces or things
like that, you know, I understand. But some things you could. Anyway,
so others say that no, it's not that you have to actively
make it part of your body. It's when you're מקפיד Makpid and
you want it off, that defines it as a חציצה. Chatzitza. So
anyway that's a big important debate about a lot of things which
there's a wide variance about whether people consider them to be חציצות
Chatzitzas or not. The final category of רוב שאינו מקפיד, Rov She-eino
Makpid, like I said, it's hard to imagine what would be an
example of רוב. Rov. Rashi says that רוב Rov applies to body
hair, right. Rashi says that רוב, Rov, and not only Rashi, other
ראשונים Rishonim say that רוב Rov applies to the hair independently. So
there could be some cases where you know you have to where
you know where where where it could be a question of רוב
Rov by the hair like I said, like hair dye is what
I was saying before about hair dye. Now you could say hair
dye is the basic פשט Pshat is that hair dye is not
the case, forget that it's an אינו Eino forget that it's not
a חציצה Chatzitza at all because it it goes into the hair
and it dyes the hair, it doesn't sit on top of the
hair, right? Yeah, like that. Right, it actually goes in. So but
but anyway, but that would be a case where there could be
cases in in theory at least where you might have a רוב
Rov would be as the hair, it's more likely than elsewhere because
of this idea that the hair might be considered separately. The final
thing that I will say about this and then we'll go on
to the מחיצה Mechitza is that you realize it's a little bit
funny because the גמרא Gemara ended by saying דבר תורה רובו ומקפיד
Devar Torah Rubo Umakpid and then it says וגזרו. Vegazru. So where
does the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai come in? Right? What
was the הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai? So Rashi says the
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai was when it's דבר תורה. Devar
Torah. That even though דבר תורה Devar Torah normally means it's based
on a פסוק, Pasuk, but here it it means that that you
know that הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai is telling us the
parameters of the פסוק. Pasuk. The פסוק Pasuk says there's a חציצה
Chatzitza idea out there and the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai
is telling us it's only defined by רוב Rov and מקפיד. Makpid.
There are some ראשונים Rishonim interestingly that, and Rashi is sort of
aware of this, that have a different גירסא Girsa or read the
גמרא Gemara differently, that actually read that no no דבר תורה Devar
Torah means that's what we learn from the פסוק, Pasuk, רוב ומקפיד.
Rov Umakpid. When we have a rabbinic גזירה Gezeira of מיעוטו ומקפיד
Mi-uto Umakpid or רוב שאינו מקפיד, Rov She-eino Makpid, that's הלכה למשה
מסיני. Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai. So Rashi says, what do you mean? That's
rabbinic, that's not הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai. But that actually
gets into an issue that sometimes the phrase הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai actually could be used for certain rabbinic enactments, and there's
a little you know
ambiguity sometimes about how precise is the term. So we normally have
a clear sense of categorization. דאורייתא De-oraita means directly based on a
פסוק. Pasuk. דרבנן De-rabbanan means rabbinically legislated. הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe
Mi-Sinai means a tradition that goes all the way back that is
not based on a פסוק Pasuk that is not an interpretation of
a פסוק. Pasuk. But sometimes הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai can
be used and הלכתא Hilchata can be used, you know, a little
bit to refer to, you know, and sometimes to a דרבנן De-rabbanan
and that's how some people actually understood this גמרא. Gemara. But anyway,
we will continue. Yeah?
Doesn't the the הלכה Halacha of כיסוי ראש Kisuy Rosh sort of
hinge upon that sortณ์ of middle ground as a הלכה למשה מסיני?
Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai?
Yeah, because גמרא Gemara says דאורייתא היא, De-oraita Hi, but it's not
really the Torah saying it. It's a similar type of
ambiguity.
Yeah. The פסוק Pasuk they probably wanted to quote was ורחץ במים
את כל בשרו. Verachatz Bamayim Et Kol Besaro.
Oh, that's a good point, במים Bamayim comes earlier. But then we
would have the דרשה Drasha כל בשרו במים. Kol Besaro Bamayim. Anyway,
alright, anyway, okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. Anyway,
so that's it seems like the conclusion was, as I said, that
biblically there's an idea of חציצה, Chatzitza, comes הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai and is lenient, and it's actually quite a big leniency,
you know, that it's not saying that every single square inch of
the body has to touch water, but that no, it has to
be directly identified as
a חציצה Chatzitza and therefore biblically you need both the majority and
מקפיד, Makpid, rabbinically only one of those. So now how about מחיצות?
Mechitzas? Is this just something a tangential conversation or is it referring
back to the concept of measuring לחומרא או לקולא? Lechumra O Lekula?
Yeah, so once we finished discussing the חומרא Chumra and the קולא
Kula in five טפח Tefach and six טפח, Tefach, now we're introducing
a related conversation. We're not going to swing back to the five
or six, but we are going but it is related because we
were talking about ways of measuring, but not about the חומרא Chumra
or the קולא. Kula. Right, exactly.
So
now now we go on to מחיצה. Mechitza. So it says
where are we? מחיצות דאורייתא נינהו. Mechitzot De-oraita Ninhu. That we can
also learn from the פסוקים. Pesukim. Where do you get that? דאמר
מר, De-amar Mar, ארון תשעה וכפורת טפח הרי כאן עשרה. Aron Tisha
Ve-chaporet Tefach Harei Kan Asara. That the ארון Aron was nine טפחים
Tefachim because it was an אמה Ama and a half. It was
nine טפחים Tefachim high and an אמה Ama six טפחים Tefachim so
it's nine. And you put on the כפורת, kapores, right, the top,
the cover, which we're assuming was a טפח. tefach. It doesn't say,
but that's the minimum, a טפח tefach measurement is a טפח. tefach.
That's ten טפחים. tefachim. And for a lot of עירובין, eiruvin, you
know, and מחיצה mechitzah in general, walls, minimum size of walls are
ten טפחים, tefachim, whether it's to designate separate רשויות, reshuyos, whether it's
the walls of a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to create a רשות
reshus for שבת, Shabbos, whether it's the minimum height of a סוכה,
sukkah, right, whether it's the wall, all these types of areas where
whether it's a wall for issues around planting in a vineyard and
כלאים, kilayim, so
walls, biblical, when there's a biblical demand or even a rabbinic demand,
whatever for walls, it's always defined by a minimum height of ten
טפחים tefachim as a divider, maybe divider's a better word than wall.
But also walls in terms of a structure of a house. For
example, what's the minimum size of a house in order to be
required for a מזוזה, mezuzah, these types of things, ten טפחים tefachim
is the normal size that we say of a divider or of
a wall of a... that's pretty short, yeah. How exactly you live
in it, anyway, but okay. So anyway, yeah, there's other requirements, it
has to be a בית
דירה, beis dirah, so now the גמרא Gemara continues one minute.
So that we can learn from the פסוק. pasuk. Now how do
you learn it from the ארון? aron? Where was the ארון? aron?
Where was it a divider? Where was it a house? Where was
it a wall? So this is based on the idea that God's
presence hovered over the ארון aron and God never came into the
airspace of the earth, if you would. God stayed up in heaven.
So
there's a famous מדרש Midrash in סוכה sukkah that says, right, God
never came within ten טפחים tefachim of the ground and משה Moshe
never came within ten טפחים tefachim of the heavens. The idea is
sort of describing in geographic terms the sense of like that impossibility
of bridging the gap between the divine and the human. So if
the divine presence hovered over the ארון aron and it didn't come,
so if the ארון aron was ten טפחים tefachim high, that shows
you that higher than ten טפחים tefachim is another zone, is another,
and therefore if you want to divide something you have to go
the whole height of the airspace of the zone to divide the
two spaces. And somehow once we figure that the airspace is ten
טפחים, tefachim, we can infer that the wall that divides two zones
is also ten טפחים. tefachim.
But משה Moshe is a lot taller than ten טפחים! tefachim! Yeah.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says, okay. So, לא צריכא
אלא לרבי יהודה. lo tzericha ela l'Rabbi Yehuda. You need it for
לרבי יהודה l'Rabbi Yehuda דאמר אמת בנין באמה בת שיתא אמת כלים
באמה בת חמשא. d'amar amas binyan b'ama bas sheisha, amas keilim b'ama
bas chamisha. So once again here we are introducing the five טפח
tefach אמה. ama. That there's a representation of לרבי יהודה l'Rabbi Yehuda
that all of the vessels in the משכן, Mishkan, including the ארון
aron and the שולחן shulchan and all of them, were measured with
a five טפח tefach אמה. ama. So that's the five טפח tefach
אמה ama we back again. So according to him, the ארון aron
with the כפורת kapores was less than ten טפחים tefachim high. So
that's not the basis of the idea of a
ten טפח tefach wall. לרבי מאיר דאמר כל האמות היו בבינונית. l'Rabbi
Meir d'amar kol ha'amos hayu b'veinonit.
All the אמות amos were average size, which means six טפח. tefach.
Exactly as we mentioned, already a little variance within the six טפחים,
tefachim, but basically they were all six טפח. tefach. מאי למימר? mai
l'meimar? How do you explain it? Because according to him ten טפחים
tefachim comes from the... you can infer that from the ארון. aron.
So the גמרא Gemara says, לרבי מאיר תשיעא הילכתא לגוד וללבוד ולדופן
עקומה. l'Rabbi Meir tisha hilchesa l'gud u'l'lavud u'l'dofen akuma.
You're right, we don't learn out the idea of מחיצה mechitzah of
the minimum height of ten טפחים, tefachim, that you can infer from
the פסוקים. pesukim. But there are other laws of מחיצה mechitzah that
are also הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. What are they? So
גוד gud is when you
imaginary, extend the wall. So if you have a wall that basically
starts going down and doesn't go all the way to the bottom,
you can envision it as if it goes all the way down.
That's what's called
גוד אחית, gud achis, you know, which is like you extend it
down. Or if it goes partway up, you could say גוד אסיק,
gud asik, which is like to extend it up. You can imagine
as if it continued up. You might remember in שבת Shabbos we
talked about being on the top of a pillar and it was
as if you were surrounded with walls because as if the side
walls extended up. So where do you get that from? הלכה למשה
מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. לבוד lavud is when something is within three
טפחים tefachim of the ground, it's like it's connected to the ground.
Or if the סכך s'chach is within three טפחים tefachim of the
wall, it's like it's connected to the wall. That's also where you
know learn that from? הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. דופן עקומה
dofen akuma we mentioned the other day, the bending wall. Right, that
if you have סכך s'chach in the middle and you can consider
the פסול סכך posul s'chach as being an extension of the wall
and bending to the middle. So all those ways that the wall
can magically bend and change and extend, that all is
הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. That's all about מחיצות, mechitzos, those
are all laws about how מחיצות mechitzos operate. לבוד lavud actually extends
beyond מחיצה, mechitzah, but a lot of these is how מחיצות mechitzos
operate. Okay, let's just start get to the bottom of the page.
That was a very central גמרא Gemara about, you know, it's quoted
elsewhere about some of the parameters of חציצה, chatzitzah, the parameters, you
know, the idea of these things being הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe
m'Sinai and so on. היה גבוה מעשרים אמה. haya gavoha m'esrim ama.
Now we're getting back to the משנה. Mishnah. If the opening of
the מבוי mavoi was higher than twenty אמה, ama, ובא למעטו, u'va
l'ma'ato, and you wanted to now lower it, כמה ממעיט? kama m'ma'it?
How much do you lower it? So גמרא Gemara says, כמה ממעיט?
kama m'ma'it? How much do you lower it? כמה דצריך ליה. kama
d'tzrich lei. How much you need to
lower
it. How about the width? Now what does that mean, the width
of what? So when you say how much do you lower it,
you would imagine what are you doing to lower the height?
It's twenty-one אמה. Ama.
What? What?
What would you do physically?
Oh, either you push, if it's like a beam, you move it
down.
So the easiest thing would be to you take the קורה, Kora,
the beam, and you lower the קורה Kora so the קורה Kora
is not on the top of the walls of the מבוי. Mavoi.
Or you fill in the top of.
That's what the רי"ף Rif says. Okay, but the,
but the רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot and everybody says that no,
the גמרא Gemara here makes it much sounds very much that what
you're doing is you're raising the floor rather than lowering the beam.
It seems like a lot more effort than it's worth. But anyway,
so the question is you're raising the floor. So here you have
the beam is over the openings of the מבוי. Mavoi. The beam
is a טפח Tefach wide. So you're raising the floor, let's say,
let's say it's one אמה, Ama, it's twenty-one אמות. Amot. So you
raise the floor one אמה. Ama. Okay, you raise it one אמה,
Ama, that I know. You raise it as much to make it
down to twenty אמות. Amot. How wide does this raised area have
to be? Does that go through the entire מבוי, Mavoi, just directly
under the beam? That's the question.
Wait, they're saying, but they'll say it can't lower the beam or
is this an alternative to lowering the beam?
Presumably an alternative, but I'll get back in a minute. Okay, so
כמה ממעיט? Kama mema'it? So I'm sorry, אלא רחבו בכמה? Ela rochvo
bekama? So what is, so what is the width of the amount
that you are raising it? So רב יוסף אמר טפח. Rav Yosef
amar Tefach. It's a טפח, Tefach, the space directly under the beam,
because the beam is assumed to be a טפח. Tefach. אביי אמר
ארבע. Abaye amar arba. אביי Abaye says it has to be four
טפחים. Tefachim. So I think we'll end here and pick up with
this tomorrow about the question about raising the space under.
Four by four which is ten by ten?
No, four by the length of the מבוי. Mavoi.
So it doesn't have to be the entire length of the מבוי.
Mavoi.